Medbh McGuckian papers, 1964-2006
Emory University
- Writings by Medbh McGuckian, Series 2; Boxes 16-30, OP 1-3
  - Poetry, Subseries 2.1; Box 16 - Box 25: Folder 45; OP 1-3
    - "The Subterfuge," MS and TS (Box 24, Folder 71)
    - "Succession," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "The Fire Tower" MS] (Box 24, Folder 72)
    - "Suivez-Moi," MS (Box 24, Folder 73)
    - "Summerson," MS (Box 24, Folder 74)
    - "Sword Sonnets," MS (Box 24, Folder 75)
    - "Tables" [See Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "Donegal" MS] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "Tavoletta," MS [See Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "The Snowflake Album," MS] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "Teaching/The Teacher," TS [variant title: "Saturday Afternoon"] (Box 24, Folder 76)
    - "A Tent," TS (Box 24, Folder 77)
    - "Thaw," TS (Box 24, Folder 78)
    - "Thinking Long," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Admiring the Furs," MS] (Box 24, Folder 79)
    - "The Thorough Bed," [See Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "Donegal," MS] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "Those People," TS (Box 24, Folder 80)
    - "Tiled Bathroom," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Two Women, Two Shores, "Children of the Mist," MS] (Box 24, Folder 81)
    - "The Tissue of Sylvius," MS (Box 24, Folder 82)
    - "To John Keats," MS [See Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "Evening Gold," MS] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "To My Daughter, Finding Her Weeping, Because I Would Not Consent to Her Fasting," MS (Box 24, Folder 83)
    - "Tobacco Hole," TS (Box 24, Folder 84)
    - "Today," TS (Box 24, Folder 85)
    - "The Tomorrow Club," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Marconi's Cottage, "The After-Thinker," MS] (Box 24, Folder 86)
    - "The Toolbook of Microsoft Windows," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Captain Lavender, "Waxwing Winter," TS] (Box 24, Folder 87)
    - "The Trough," TS (Box 24, Folder 88)
    - "Truganini," TS (Box 24, Folder 89)
    - "The Turning," MS (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - "Turning the Sligo Spindle," MS (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - "Two Heliotropes," MS (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - "The Uncrossed "t" in Father," MS (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - "Up the River," TS (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - "Us," MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - "Valentina," TS [variant title "Zero-G"] [See also Subseries 2.1, Portrait of Joanna, "Power-Cut," MS] (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - "The Villa," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Venus and the Rain, "Sabbath Park," TS] (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - "The Vine Forestlight," MS (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - "Vintage," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "Donegal," MS] (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - "The Voice Coach," MS (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - "The Washeteria," TS (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - "Watching the Owls With You," MS (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - "Waterford," TS (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - "The Weaver-Girl," TS (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - "Wedlock," TS (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - "Whimbrel," MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - "Wife Swapping," TS (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - "The Window," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Theatre," TS, and Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "Hands," MS] (Box 25, Folder 19)
    - "Winter," TS (Box 25, Folder 20)
    - "A Winter One Cannot Explain," MS (Box 25, Folder 21)
    - "Women's Names," MS (Box 25, Folder 22)
    - "Wonderland," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Perfect Mother," TS] (Box 25, Folder 23)
    - "The Wooden Girl," MS (Box 25, Folder 24)
    - "The Yellow Path," MS [variant title: "A Beach More Than a House"] (Box 25, Folder 25)
    - "Yellow Ultramarine," MS (Box 25, Folder 26)
    - "Yesterday's Bather," MS and proof [See Subseries 2.1, The Currach Requires No Harbours, "Orant Figure," proof, and Subseries 2.1, Uncollected Individual Poems, "Painting a Verb," MS] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "You Were Not In," MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 27)
    - "Zero Eighteen," MS (Box 25, Folder 28)
    - Untitled, "As for us, we dream of the first sea," MS (Box 25, Folder 29)
    - Untitled, "Half-an-hour away, in the far north," MS (Box 25, Folder 30)
    - Untitled, "How poor the light is on the [slate]," MS (Box 25, Folder 31)
    - Untitled, "I must be in love with never because," MS (Box 25, Folder 32)
    - Untitled, "I wasn't feeling too hot, myself," MS (Box 25, Folder 33)
    - Untitled, "In the sweep of sky that I miss," MS (Box 25, Folder 34)
    - Untitled, "It waits until it is discovered," MS (Box 25, Folder 35)
    - Untitled, "It was not as the snow said, forever waving," MS (Box 25, Folder 36)
    - Untitled, "The leaves' brown breasts," MS (Box 25, Folder 37)
    - Untitled, "Midway between one house and another," MS (Box 25, Folder 38)
    - Untitled, "Starless, moonless, my kremlin heart," MS (Box 25, Folder 39)
    - Untitled, "Where horses had been grazing the year before, we met," MS (Box 25, Folder 40)
    - Untitled, "Yesterday's words have too much," MS (Box 25, Folder 41)
    - Poem fragments (Box 25, Folder 42)
    - Notes (Box 25, Folder 43)
    - Notes (Box 25, Folder 44)
    - Notes (Box 25, Folder 45)
  - Prose, Subseries 2.2; Box 25: Folder 46 - Box 27: Folder 12
    Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - "21 Cloneen," TS and proof [with ANS, undated, from Ciaran Carson] (Box 25, Folder 46)
    - "And Cry Jesus to the Mice," MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 47)
    - "As Prisoned Birds," TS (Box 25, Folder 48)
    - Autobiographical notes, MS (Box 25, Folder 49)
    - "Bawling Across the Hearthrug," [re: Paul Durcan and Seán Dunne] MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 50)
    - "Belfast," TS (Box 25, Folder 51)
    - Biographical notes on Anne Devlin and Jennifer Johnston, TS (Box 25, Folder 52)
    - "Birds and Their Masters" [re: Eavan Boland], TS (Box 25, Folder 53)
    - "A Birthday Letter," MS (Box 25, Folder 54)
    - "The Bounty and the Malice," [review of Jo Slade's The Vigilant One] TS (Box 25, Folder 55)
    - "Cheshire Cat" [review of Norman Dugdale's Running Repairs; The Selected Roy McFadden, ed. John Boyd; Padraid Fiacc's Odour of Blood; and Tom Paulin's Liberty Tree], MS (Box 25, Folder 56)
    - "County Down," TS (Box 25, Folder 57)
    - "The Dancehall of the Mind," [review of two anthologies of Irish poetry: Pillas of the Horse and Silver Apples, Golden Apples] MS (Box 25, Folder 58)
    - "Don't Talk to Me About Dance" [review of Rita Ann Higgins's Philomena's Revenge] TS (Box 25, Folder 59)
    - "Freya's Party," MS (Box 25, Folder 60)
    - "Full of Consciousness" [review of Rita Kelly's Fare Well--Beir Beannacht] MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 61)
    - "Gardener Outside the Walls" [review of Francis Stuart's We Have Kept the Faith] MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 62)
    - Gothic Influence on Nineteenth Century Anglo-Irish Fiction [written by McGuckian as "Maeve T.P. McCaughan"], Dissertation for M.A. at Queens University, Belfast, 1973, TS [ 1 of 2] (Box 25, Folder 63)
    - Gothic Influence on Nineteenth Century Anglo-Irish Fiction, TS [ 2 of 2] (Box 25, Folder 64)
    - "Half a Full Moon," TS [variant title: "Twins"] [with TLS, 17 June 2000, from Brendan Barrington] (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - "The Hawk and I," [review of Francis Stuart's We Have Kept the Faith] TS (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - "Helen's Story-A War Story," MS (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - "Holy Family Parish is the story of my childhood," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Horsepower, Pass By! A Study of the Car in the Poetry of Seamus Heaney, TS and notes (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - "A House of Female Habitation," [review of The Faber Book of Twentieth-Century Women's Poetry] TS (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - "How being Irish has influenced me as a writer and a woman," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - "How Precious Also Are Thy Thoughts Unto Me" [review of Marina Tsvetaeva's Art in the Light of Conscience], TS and proof (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - "The Idea of an Anglo-Irish Poetic Tradition," MS [MS notes by Heaney] (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - "Inching In," [review of John Hughes's Something in Particular] MS (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - "Irish Women Poets and Nationalism," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - "It's Six Miles from Bangor[?] to Donaghadee," MS (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - "Jack's Holm," proof [See Subseries 2.1: Shelmalier, "Home Daughter"] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "A Kind of English" [review of Amy Clampitt's The Kingfisher], MS (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - "Ladies' Night Apostles," [review of Word of Mouth] TS (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - "Like Yeats: Rhetorical Questions," MS (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - "Making a Meal of It," [review of Tom Paulin's Walking a Line] TS (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - "My Sense of Identity," TS (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - "A Notebook of Women Writers," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - "On Moortown," [re: Ted Hughes] MS (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - "On River," [re: Ted Hughes] MS (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - "On the Back of the Swallow," [re: Danny Morrison] MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - "P.J.," MS (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - "Patrick Kavanagh: An Appraisal," TS (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - "A Picture Two Lives Deep," [review of Sara Berkeley's Penn] MS (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - "Pilgrimage in Long Shorts," [review of Frank Ormsby's A Northern Spring] MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - Portrait of the Artist as a Young Girl [autobiographical novel], MS (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - Presentation: "How Far Can Creative Writing Be Taught?," MS (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - Radio Script: "The Wreck of the Hesperus," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - Radio Script: Untitled, MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - "Rathlin Road," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - "Re-inventing Our History" [review of Moyra Donaldson's Snakeskin Stilettos], TS (Box 26, Folder 31)
    - "Rescuers and White Cloaks: Diary, 1968-69," TS (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - Review of Nuala Archer's Between Swilly and Sewanee, MS (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Review of Cammy Thomas's Cathedral of Wish, MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - Review of Brian Walker and Alf McCreary's Degrees of Excellence: The Story of Queen's, Belfast 1845-1995, TS (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - Review of Audrey Scales's The Ephemeral Isle, MS (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - Review of Robert McLiam Wilson's Eureka Street, TS (Box 26, Folder 37)
    - Review of Alice Milligan's The Harper of the Only God: Selected Poems, TS (Box 26, Folder 38)
    - Review of Lives of Irish Artists, ed. Dr. Brian P. Kennedy, TS (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - Review of Siobhan Campbell's The Permanent Wave and Josephine Balmer's Classical Women Poets, MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 40)
    - Review of Seamus Deane's Reading in the Dark, TS (Box 26, Folder 41)
    - Review of John Montague's and Ted Hughes's Selected Poems, TS (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - Review of Moyra Donaldson's Snakeskin Stilettos, TS (Box 26, Folder 43)
    - "Skrimshadering, Or Not the Rupert Bear School" [review of Faber Book of Political Verse] MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 44)
    - "Something of a Mystery" [review of John Booth's Jack B. Yeats: A Vision of Ireland] MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 45)
    - "The State of Poetry," TS (Box 26, Folder 46)
    - "Summer Books 1991," MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 47)
    - "Surreal Ireland," MS (Box 26, Folder 48)
    - "The Sweet of Pillage," TS (Box 26, Folder 49)
    - "Teaching Poetry and Poetry for Pleasure," MS (Box 26, Folder 50)
    - "That Obvious Thing That Nobody Does" [review of Ruth Carr's There Is a House, Padraic Fiacc's Semper Vacare, and Ciaran Carson's The Ballad of HMS Belfast], MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 51)
    - "To Pour is To Fill," [review of Lionel Shriver's The Female of the Species] MS (Box 26, Folder 52)
    - "Who Was Who?," [review of Anne Ulry Colman's A Dictionary of 19th Century Irish Women Poets] MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 53)
    - "Women Are Trousers," TS (Box 26, Folder 54)
    - "Women in Anglo-Irish Literature," MS (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - "Your thoughts about how your own work connects with this tradition of women writers," TS (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Untitled [article on Michael Longley and religion], MS (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Untitled: "The first summer we went to sea," MS (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Untitled: "I had a friendship," MS (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Untitled: "I suppose my own personal development," MS (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Untitled: "I was thinking today about the hunger strike," MS (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Untitled: "It was something," MS (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Untitled [summary of research at the Irish Institute], TS (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Untitled prose, MS (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous fragments (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous fragments (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Translations by McGuckian, Subseries 2.3; Box 27: Folders 13-62
    Arranged in alphabetical order by author.
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "Adriana," MS (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "The Blonde Beast" ["Fiara"], MS (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "A Day-and-a-Half for the Banana-Fish" ["O zi minunata pentru pestele-banana"], MS (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "Do You Know a Countryside Where the Lemon Trees Are in Bloom?" ["Cunosti tu tara unde infloresc lamii?"], MS (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "I'm Smiling" ["Zimbesc"], MS (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "My Everyday Dream" ["Visul meu familiar"], MS (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "Slightly in Mourning" ["Mica elegie"], MS (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "Three Brothers Vodka" ["O vodka la, 'caraimanul'"], MS (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "To an Artist" ["La o artist?"], MS (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea: "When Love's What You Need" ["Cind ai nevoie de dragoste"], MS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, "Adriana," MS] (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Kruit, Johanna: "Birds Leaving" ["Vogeltrek"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Kruit, Johanna: "Giving Way," TS [variant title: "The Way of the Water"] ["De weg van het water"] [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Kruit, Johanna: "Birds Leaving," MS] (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - Mac Lochlainn, Gearóid, "Going with the Flow" ["Sruth na Teangan"], "The Voice of Her" [A Glór], "Flying" ["Ag Eitilt"], "First Steps," MS and TS [with ALS, undated, from Gearóid Mac Lochlainn to McGuckian] (Box 27, Folder 25)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Aubade," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala, "The Bond"] (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "The Bond" ["Geasa"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Cadenza," TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "X-Ray Weather Bulletin," MS and TS] (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Daphne and Apollo," TS (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Devil's Tattoo" ["Stigmata"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 30)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "The Ebony Adonis" ["An Prionsa Dubh"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 31)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Eithne the Hun" ["Eithne Uathach"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 32)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "The Furnace" ["An Fhoirnéis"], MS and TS [variant title: "Autchwitz"] (Box 27, Folder 33)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "A God Shows Up" ["Teacht an Dé"], MS and TS [variant title: "Out with a God"] (Box 27, Folder 34)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Night Fishing" ["Iascach Oiche"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Nine Little Goats" [An Casadh"], MS (Box 27, Folder 36)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Persephone Suffering from SAD" ["Peirsifine"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 37)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Primavera," MS and TS [variant title: "March, 1998"] (Box 27, Folder 38)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "The Prodigal Muse" ["Filleadh na Béithe"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 39)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Slaughter" ["An Slad"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 40)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "The Snow Queen" ["Banríon an Tsneachta"], MS and TS [variant title: "Her Majesty in 'Iceland'"] (Box 27, Folder 41)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Ten Ways of Looking at a Magpie" ["An Snag Breac"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 42)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "The Tragic Legend of the Children of Lir" ["Oidhe Chlainne Lir"], TS (Box 27, Folder 43)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Winter Beachhead" ["Tráigh Gheimhridh"], MS and TS [variant titles: "Winter Strand" and "Beachhead, January 1998"] (Box 27, Folder 44)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "Words for the Branwen Theme" ["Focail do Théama Bhranwen"], TS (Box 27, Folder 45)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala: "X-Ray Weather Bulletin" ["Faisnéis na hAimsire Inmheánaí], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 46)
    - Ó Searcaigh, Cathal: "For My Father" [Do m'athair], MS (Box 27, Folder 47)
    - Ó Searcaigh, Cathal: "The Outcast" ["An Díbeartach"], MS (Box 27, Folder 48)
    - Tillema, Mieke: "Considering Tulips" ["Van Tulpen"], TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Kruit, Johanna: "Birds Leaving," MS] (Box 27, Folder 49)
    - Tillema, Mieke: "Feminist Genesis" ["Terra Tabu"], TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Kruit, Johanna: "Birds Leaving," MS] (Box 27, Folder 50)
    - Tillema, Mieke: "In Memoriam Patris," TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Kruit, Johanna: "Birds Leaving," MS] (Box 27, Folder 51)
    - Tillema, Mieke: "Our Inner Future" ["Toekomende Tijd"], TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Warmond, Ellen, "Changement de Décor," MS] (Box 27, Folder 52)
    - Tillema, Mieke: "So Soon" ["Zo Vroeg"], MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations by McGuckian, Kruit, Johanna: "Birds Leaving," MS] (Box 27, Folder 53)
    - Van de Kamp, Peter: "Mirrors Again" ["Weer Spiegelt"], TS (Box 27, Folder 54)
    - Van Haren, Elma: "Stepping Out With Edward Munch" ["Op Stap Met Edvard Munch"], MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 55)
    - Van Hee, Miriam: "Spring Rain" ["Deze Lente"], TS (Box 27, Folder 56)
    - Warmond, Ellen: "Changement de Décor," MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 57)
    - Unknown author: "The Look of Love," lyrics, MS and TS (Box 27, Folder 58)
    - Unidentified translations (Box 27, Folder 59)
    - Galley proofs of McGuckian's translations from the Dutch, publisher's correspondence, and off-print of interview with McGuckian and poems by McGuckian (Box 27, Folder 60)
    - Draft poems and correspondence related to McGuckian's translations of Dutch poetry (Box 27, Folder 61)
    - Instructions for submitting translation, extract from the Official Journal of the European Communities (Box 27, Folder 62)
  - Translations of McGuckian, Subseries 2.4; Box 27: Folders 63-69
    - "An Colmán Aille," Art Hughes, undated [translation of "The Rock Dove"], TS (Box 27, Folder 63)
    - "Feachtas Gharraí an Mhargaidh," Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill, undated [translation of "Operation Market Garden"], TS (Box 27, Folder 64)
    - "Masca de Gaze a lui Mickey Mouse," Mircea Cartarescu, undated [translation of "The Mickey-Mouse Gas Mask"], TS (Box 27, Folder 65)
    - "Matematic, Cel Putin O Usa," Mircea Cartarescu, undated [translation of "Mathematically, at Least a Door"], TS (Box 27, Folder 66)
    - Nu kommer de!!!, undated (Box 27, Folder 67)
    - Poesie der Nachbarn, undated [translations of "Harem Trousers," "Villian," "Moonshots," "Head of a Woman," "Ceramic and Wood for Bronze," "Cloth Mother," "The Truth Room," "Next Day Hill," "Still Life of Eggs"] (Box 27, Folder 68)
    - "Rós Síleála Duilleogach," Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill, undated [translation of "Foliage Ceiling Rose"], TS (Box 27, Folder 69)
  - Notebooks, Subseries 2.5; Box 28 - Box 30
    - Notebook with poetry [includes poetry from Portrait of Joanna, The Flower Master and Other Poems, The Butterfly Farm, The Maiden Aunt, The Marzipan Room, and "After the Fire" and "Déjà Vu"] (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from Portrait of Joanna, The Flower Master and Other Poems, Venus and the Rain, and Two Women, Two Shores] (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from Portrait of Joanna and The Butterfly Farm and "Teaching/The Teacher"] (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from The Flower Master and Other Poems] (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from The Flower Master and Other Poems and Venus and the Rain] (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from The Flower Master and Other Poems and Two Women, Two Shores] (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Amelia," and "The Snow Poem"] (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from Venus in the Rain, Two Women, Two Shores, "Poem for a Lost Birthday"] (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from Marconi's Cottage] (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes translations and poetry from Captain Lavender and Shelmalier] (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from Shelmalier and Drawing Ballerinas] (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Notebook with notes on tables of contents and poetry [includes poetry from The Face of the Earth and other uncollected poems] (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from The Currach Requires No Harbours] (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes poetry from The Maiden Aunt] (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes "Choice" and "Story County"] (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Notebook with notes and poetry [includes "Man of War Bird," "A Perfume Called 'My Own,'" and "The Modern Proserpine"] (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Notebook with uncollected poetry (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Notebook with notes and drafts of Horsepower Pass By!: A Study of the Car in the Poetry of Seamus Heaney (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Notebook with class compositions (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Notebook with class notes (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Notebook with class notes, notes for a review, and poetry fragments (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Notebook with essays on literature (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Notebook with essays on poetry (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Notebook with poems by others in McGuckian's hand (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Two notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Three notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Four notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Four notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Four notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Four notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Five notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Five notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Five notebooks with fragments of poetry (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Two notebooks with juvenilia (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous pages from notebooks (Box 30, Folder 7)
- Writings by others, Series 3; Box 31 - Box 38
  The series includes a variety of works written by students and other writers. Present are typescripts of critical writings about McGuckian as well as creative work by other writers and by students to whom McGuckian taught creative writing. Printed writings by others are found in Subseries 5.2.
  Organized into three subseries: (3.1) Writings about McGuckian, (3.2) Other prose, and (3.3) Poetry.
  - Writings about Medbh McGuckian, Subseries 3.1; Box 31 - Box 32a
    - Bedient, Calvin, Poetry of a New Beyond: Medbh McGuckian's Marconi's Cottage, 1994, TS (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Brandes, Rand, Interview with Medbh McGuckian, 1996, TS (Box 31, Folder 2)